hello everybody and welcome to part two
各位你们好，欢迎来到本教程的
in this gmod people do it saucers now in
第二部分，现在
this video again we're not gonna be
在这一期视频里，我们不会
learning too much but what we will be
学习太多内容，但我们要做的
doing is we will be showing you how to
是向你展示如何
basically run a script inside of Garry's
在GMOD里运行一些最基本的脚本
Mod so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna go
接下来我会继续我们的主题
ahead and I will open up sublime I'm
我要打开Sublime(译者注:现在更推荐使用VSCode+Lua+Glua插件)
gonna go to file new file just like
然后点击文件选项，创建新文件，就像
normal
平常一样
remember based on whichever text editor
请记住由于你用的编辑器不同
you're using this may be different but
这一步可能是不同的，但
normally it's the same for all I'm just
大体上都是相似的，好那么
gonna go ahead and hit ctrl s to save
我继续，按下ctrl+S组合键保存文件
I'm then gonna go over to where garry's
然后我将打开GMOD
mod is installed steam library steam
在STEAM库下的安装路径
apps common Garry's Mod then go to
这一般在SteamLibrary/common/apps/Garry's Mod这个路径下
Garry's Mod again and then go ahead and
然后继续打开
go into newer sorry and then here is
LUA文件夹。 这里就是_
where you're gonna want to save it so
你保存你的LUA代码的地方
for example I'm just gonna save this as
在这次演示里我会把这个文件保存为
test dot lower now remember it's got to
test.lua，请记住你必须
be a Lua file so if we go ahead and say
把文件保存为lua后缀，接着我们继续
that now you can get the gmod low Alexa
现在你可以打开GMOD LUA语法高亮
which is done by F jpg I remember his
这个是由FJPG...我不记得他的名字了
name there will be a link in the
语法高亮插件链接我会
description to that that's if you're
放在简介里
using sublime but I know there is also
如果你使用的是sublime的话对你很有帮助，我知道也有
one for Adam and notepad plus plus so if
给Atom和NP++制作的_
you using even one of those it will also
如果你在用这些编辑器的话也可以使用
work now in here we're gonna write our
这些插件。（再次安利VSCODE，只要在扩展商店里搜索Glua即可） 现在我们
script I was good it's gonna be very
要开始写第一个脚本了，这会非常
simple it's just gonna simply be print
简单，就是像我写的这样，一句
hello world just like that now you'll
print("hello,world")完事，你会注意到
notice how we don't have the i/o dot
注意到我们并没有写什么io.read
read on here which we did in my lure
尽管我们在lua系列教程里_
tutorial series and that's because
是这样做的，因为（注:这里是在讨论为何不用打开lua文件的问题，初学者可以略过）
Garry's Mod is is running this as the
GMOD把这些载入的LUA作为环境运行了
environment meaning if our script gets
这意味着即使我们的脚本
to the end of the code Garry's Mod it's
被执行到了最后一行代码，GMOD
still gonna be running so it doesn't
仍然在运行，所以这个脚本文件
close so IO doc read it's not needed
不需要关闭，所以IO.read()并不需要
anymore just simply print hello world so
只需要简单的打印hello world就行
let's then go into a gmod will then
然后我们打开GMOD，接着
start up a single-player game and once
启动单人游戏
we're in the game there we go we're
然后我们继续
gonna go ahead and we're gonna go into
接着我们打开(默认按~键，请注意是否启用控制台)控制台
our console I'm will type Lua and the
接着输入lua_openscript_cl
score open open script and there's
called CL and then you simply start type
接下来你只需要输入
in the name of your script in this case
你脚本的文件名，在我这里
ours was test a lure we do that we hit
是test.lua，然后我们敲下
enter and as you can see it says it's
回车键，接下来正如你所看到的
running the script and then it says
脚本运行了，然后它打印了一句
hello world so the first thing you'll
hello world，你会注意到第一件事
notice is that this is now our
这是运行在控制台里的
so with before we had the e terminal on
在我们有图形化界面终端之前
Windows this is now our console so yeah
我们的代码是跑在这个控制台里的
that's pretty much that we can also do
说得太多了，接下来我们可以
Lua underscore open scripts and instead
输入lua_openscript，没有后面的
of doing an underscore CL we just simply
_cl，我们只是
type open script and type of test and as
输入lua_openscript，然后空一格输入test.lua
you can see it did the exact same except
接下来你会看到结果基本一致，除了
this time our text was in blue and if
这次我们打印出的文本是蓝色的
you remember our client and server
如果你还对上节关于客户端和服务端的内容有印象的话
tutorial I said the orange was client
你应该记得我说过，橙色代表客户端
and blue was the server so when we went
而蓝色代表服务端，所以如果我们在客户端上执行的话
on our client you'll notice how the text
也就是用lua_openscript_cl，你会发现
is orange moving around on the server
文本是橙色的，如果在服务端执行的话
our text is blue and as I've already
得到的就是蓝色的，就像我此前说过的
stated in that video there is a client
即使是在一个单人模式的游戏里
and server even though I'm on single
依然有客户端和服务端的概念
player there is basically a server with
游戏会建立一个只有一个玩家位置的
one slot for you to join that is not
服务器来给你加入，这个服务器并没有
hosted on the internet but on your local
搭建在互联网上，而是建立在
game so again there is still a client on
你本地的游戏上，所以在强调一次永远都有客户端和
the server now I hope that really makes
服务端的概念，希望你能记住
sense to you again I know this is
这很重要。我知道这已经不是上一期了
another short video but the idea of this
这一期的视频是想教会你
video is just to give you a name
只是想给你一个简单的说明
explanation on how we can go ahead and
来展示我们接下来将怎样
write and execute scripts now one thing
编写和执行脚本，现在还有一件
to know is that for now we're gonna be
你需要知道的事情是，我们接下来
doing all of our work inside of that Lua
所做的一切都是在lua文件夹下
folder that I told you to save in now
就像我之前让你保存的地方一样
once we obviously get a bit further on
当我们更深入的学习的时候
we're gonna go ahead and we're gonna
我们将会进一步
convert those into add-ons rather than
把我们的脚本转换为插件(add-ons)并放在addons文件夹下
having to place them into the newer
而不是放在lua文件夹下
folder but yeah I hope you learned
希望你从这简短的视频里
something and again I do apologize for
有所收获，我很抱歉
it be in such a short video these are
这期视频如此简短
just designed to give you the
这是为了能够
introductory of what we need to get
让你循序渐进的学习
started so again if you have any
然后，再说一次，如果你有任何
questions leave a comment I hope you
疑问的话，可以在评论区留下你的评论（译者注:我也会尽力解答的）
learned something I hope you enjoyed
希望你学到一些东西，并且很愉快的看完了
watching and I'll see you in the next
这期视频，让我们下期见
video
you